<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A little catechisme, that is to say, a short instruction touching christian religion, set forth by Theodorus Beza Minister of the Church of God in Geneua</title>
            <title>Petit catéchisme. English.</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09959</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120273</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855472</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855472</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09959)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 411:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A little catechisme, that is to say, a short instruction touching christian religion, set forth by Theodorus Beza Minister of the Church of God in Geneua</title>
                  <title>Petit catéchisme. English.</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Hugh Singleton, dwelling in Creede Lane, at the signe of the Gilden Tunn. nere vnto Ludgate. Cum priuilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1578]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Bèze, Théodore de. Petit catéchisme, c'est-à-dire  sommaire instruction de la religion chrestienne.</note>
                  <note>Caption title. Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformed Church --  Catechisms --  English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:20967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20967:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A little Catechiſme, that is <hi>to ſay, a ſhort inſtruction touching chriſtian</hi> religion, ſet forth by Theodorus Beza <hi>Miniſter of the Church of God in Geneua.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>The firſt ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion. 1 <hi>WHerefore hath God placed vs in this world?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aunſwere.</hi> To know and ſerue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>2.</hi> Wil he be knowen and ſerued according to our vnderstanding and will: or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that, which it hath pleaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to declare and ſet out vnto vs touching the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> According to that which he hath declared vnto vs concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>3.</hi> Where hath he declared and ſet out the ſame vnto vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In that booke which we call the Bible, comprehending, togither with diuers hiſtories, the law and the goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>4.</hi> Who hath made this booke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God him ſelfe, by the miniſterye of hys holy Prophets and Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> What is the law?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The doctrine which teacheth vs what we ought to do, as well towards God, as one of vs towards an other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> What is the Goſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20967:2"/>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That heauenly doctrine which teacheth vs, what we muſt beleeue to our ſaluation thorow Ieſus Chriſt only.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>7.</hi> Doth this word conteine al that which we must beleeue and doe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea, without hauing any neede to adde or ioyne any thing thereto, or to take anye thing therefrom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>8.</hi> Say now the articles of your beleefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I beleue in God, the father almighty. &amp;c</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>The ſecond ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. <hi>Doth this Doctrine teach vs, that there is but one onely God, or that there are more gods then one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It teacheth that there is but one God only, and that we may not haue more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> Wherfore ſay you ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it muſt needes be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he whiche is God, ſhould be aboue all other thinges, and therfore he may not haue a fellowe or companion ioyned with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> Yet you in naming God haue ſeemed to rehearſe three, that is to ſay, the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In deede there are three perſons, in one only Godhead: but yet theſe three perſons, are but one, and the ſelfe ſame onely God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> Meane you that God is diuided into three partes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for God can not be diuided, but I
<pb facs="tcp:20967:2"/>ſay, that euery one of theſe three perſons is one, and the ſelfe ſame onely God altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there perfect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> How can this be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a miſterie or ſecreat beyonde al our vnderſtanding, and yet notwythſtandyng moſt certayne and ſure, for God hath ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it and ſet it forth vnto vs, by hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> Doe you then beleeue in one onelye God, the father the ſonne, and the holy ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea: and by Gods goodnes, will. dye in this faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>The third ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>1.</hi> How is the ſonne of God called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> IESVS CHRIST.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> What meane theſe wordse IESVS CHRIST?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Ieſus</hi> is as much to ſay, as Sauior, and <hi>Christe</hi> is as muche as annoynted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to be our ſoueraigne king, hauing power ouer all creatures, our ſoueraigne or high prophet, who hath fullye declared vnto vs the wyl of God his father, touching our ſaluation, and our ſoueraigne or high prieſte, which hath fullye appeaſed an paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the wrathe of God agaynſte vs for our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> What hath hee done and ſuffered to ſaue vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20967:3"/>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He was conceiued by the holy ghoſte, and borne of the virgin Mary, ſuffered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pontius Pilate, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> Can God ſuffer or dye?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> Is not Ieſus Christ true and very God, eternall, with his father and the holy ghost?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A,</hi> Yea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> How then is he ſayd to haue dyed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that being verye God, he was made man alſo, to the end that in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon our nature mighte beare or ſuffer the whole puniſhment due to our ſinnes and traunſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>7.</hi> Doe you meane that the ſonne of God, was changed into man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, becauſe then he ſhould be no more God: and god can not eyther change him ſelfe or be changed. But being of himſelfe verye God, he hath taken our nature vnto himſelfe, that ſo he might be very god and very man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>8.</hi> If he had not bin God coulde he haue bin our ſauiour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for it belongeth vnto God onely to pardon and forgiue ſins, and to giue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 9. <hi>And if he had not bin man, coulde he haue bin our ſauiour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If he had not bin man he could not haue
<pb facs="tcp:20967:3"/>dyed, and therefore we our ſelues ſhoulde haue bin ſubiect vnto death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>The fourth ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 1. <hi>Shall all the world be ſaued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for the greater part of the world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their ſaluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> Who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they which ſhal be ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They that haue faith and beleeue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> And what is fayth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A certaine perſwaſion and aſſurance, which euery true chriſtian man oughte to-haue, that God the father loueth him, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſons ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> Wherefore doe you ſay for Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes ſake?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that we being altogither cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and wholly peruerſe in our ſelues, God could not loue vs, but in reſpecte of him onely, which is man altogither iuſte and perfect, that is to ſay Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> Commeth this fayth of our ſelues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, but from the onely grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, which doth frely giue it to his elect and choſen ones.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> And they which haue this fayth, are they ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea of neceſſitie, for god hath giuen his ſonne to the ende that euery one which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth in him, ſhould haue life euerlaſting:
<pb facs="tcp:20967:4"/>and he is not a lyer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>The fifth ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>1.</hi> But wherby may a man knowe whether he haue fayth or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By good workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> Which be good woorkes, and which be euill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe onely are good which he himſelfe hath commanded, and thoſe euill which he hath forbidden.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> Rehearſe nowe the commandements of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Heare Iſraell &amp;c. The ſumme wherof is, thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> To knowe Gods commandements, is not onely to know to ſay them, but men must alſo vnderstand that which they ſay: wherfore I demaund of you, what meaneth that which is ſayd in the third commaundement, to take the name of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is to name God, which we muſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doe, but vpon iuſt and good cauſe, and with feare of his maieſty whom we name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> Then it is by stronger and greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more forbidden to ſweare by God in vain that is to ſay, to take him for a witnes and iudge, without iust and good cauſe why.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is ſo in deede,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> What meaneth it to ſanctifie the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth day, or day of rest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20967:4"/>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is to dedicate and conſecrate it to the glory of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>7.</hi> Ought we not alſo to dedicate vnto him all the rest of the dayes of our life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea, but this day is particularlye and cheefely ordayned for this end and purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>8.</hi> Doe men forbid to trauaile or worke on the Saboth day, as though to labor were a thing euill of it ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, but they forbid ordinary and vſuall labor, to doe a worke which is better and more profitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>The ſixt ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>1.</hi> You haue ſayde that they only are good workes which God hath commanded. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tell me can we accompliſh and fulfyll the commandements of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, not ſo muche as begin to doe anye thing, but by a certaine ſinguler and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grace of God. Yea there neuer hath bin or ſhall be a man, excepting Ieſus Chriſte only, which hath perfectly fulfilled y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> Wherefore ſay you ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God will ſaue vs thorowe his only mercy in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>3.</hi> Yet ſo it is that a good lyfe is the way to ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is true that repentaunce and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ioyned with the forgiuenes of our ſinnes: but yet it followeth not therevppon,
<pb facs="tcp:20967:5"/>that we be ſaued by our workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> And why ſhall we not be ſaued by our workes ſeing that they are good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they be not good inough for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> Wherefore then are they good?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To ſette forth Gods honor: to winne or elſe to ſtrengthen our neighbors, and to make vs know and feele in our ſelues, that we are the children of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> Good workes then make vs not Gods children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for contrariwiſe a man muſt firſte be the child of GOD, before he can doe good woorkes: but this is a marke or badge, whereby men may knowe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>7.</hi> What then maketh vs the children &amp; ſonnes of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The onely grace and mercye of God, by his holy ſpirite, becauſe he hath elected and choſen vs from before all euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, according to his good pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>The ſeuenth ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>1.</hi> The holy ghost then is hee which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs the children of god: but what instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or meanes, doth he ordinarily &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſe to bring vs to that honor and kepe vs in the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The preaching of the word praier, and
<pb facs="tcp:20967:5"/>the vſe of the ſacraments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> What call you preaching of the word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An expoſition of the writinges of the Prophets and Apoſtls, which is don in the Churche, by ſuch as he hath called to that holy miniſtery: of Whom it is ſayd the that receiueth you receiueth me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> And how doe you pray?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Saying. O our father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> To whom ſpeake you theſe wordes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To God the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> How is he your father, ſeeing that he hath but one onely ſonne, that is to ſay IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS CHRIST?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe that Ieſus Chriſte hys eternal ſonne being made man, is become our brother: ſecondly, becauſe he loueth me in Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a fatherly loue and affection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>6.</hi> Albeit then that you directe not your ſpeach and wordes eyther to the ſonne or to the holy ghoste, yet you doe not exclud or ſhutte out eyeher the one or the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, For I can not call him Father, but in the name of his ſonne IESVS CHRISTE, nor praye vnto hym
<pb facs="tcp:20967:6"/>but by the holy ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>7.</hi> And is it not lawfull for a man to frame or make his prayer to the perſon of the ſonne and of the holy ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yea in deede. For ſeeing that the three perſons are one onely, and the ſelfe ſame God, inuocation or prayer dooth equallye belong vnto them. And whether I call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the father in the name of the ſonne by the holy ghoſt, or that I make my prayer vnto the ſonne to leade and bring mee to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or that I pray the holy ghoſt to teache me the father and the ſonne, all commeth to one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>The eyght ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>1.</hi> And what is a Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a thing which God ſetteth before mens eyes in his church, to ſignify vnto vs for our ſaluation, an other thing which men ſee not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> And wherfore hath God ordeined theſe ſignes to his promiſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For to make vs ſo much the more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the certainty of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> How many ſuch ſignes are there in the christian Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two, that is to ſay, Baptiſme, and the holy Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> What ſee you in Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Water.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20967:6"/>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> What dothe thys water ſignifye vnto you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>6.</hi> To what end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To make cleane my ſins, as the water being occupyed, maketh cleane the filthines of the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>7.</hi> Doth this water make cleane and purge ſinnes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, but it ſignifyeth vnto me that which waſheth my ſinnes, to wit, the bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>8.</hi> Meane you that this matter or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the bloud of Ieſus Christe waſheth our ſoules?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for our ſoules can not be clenſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any matter as our bodyes. But thys bloude maketh me cleane, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſus Chriſte hath ſhed it for ſatiſfaction and full recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>9.</hi> Is there then anye difference betweene the water of Baptiſme, and common water?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, as concerning the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (for it is alwayes water) but there is very great difference, as concerning the vſe: for the common water ſerueth to waſh and make cleane our bodilye filthineſſes, and the water vſed in Baptiſme, is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, of the waſhing of our ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>The ninth ſection.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:20967:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>1.</hi> What ſee you in the ſupper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The bread and the wine, which is there giuen and receiued according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and inſtitution of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> What doth this breade and this wine ſignifie vnto you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The bread ſignifieth to me, the bodye crucified for mee, and the wine ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth vnto mee, the bloudde ſhedde out for me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> To what end?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To teſtifie vnto me, &amp; to aſſure me, that euen as this bread &amp; this wine, are ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> maintenance and nouriſhment of this life, ſo our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte hath giuen his body &amp; his bloud for me, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe to mee, to the ende that from him, as from a fountaine there may flowe vnto me eternal life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> Are this bread and wine our ſpirituall nouriſhment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, but they ſignifie vnto vs that from whence verye eternall lyfe it ſelfe proceedeth, that is to ſaye, from hym which hath ſuffered his death and paſſion to take away the cauſe of our death, that is to ſay ſins, and to renue vs vnto eternall life, thorow a ſpiritual liuelines, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth and remaineih in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>5.</hi> Is there anye difference betweene the
<pb facs="tcp:20967:7"/>bread and wine vſed in this ſacrament, and common bread and wine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, as touching the matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce (for it is alwayes bread and wine) but there is very great difference, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the vſe: for ordinary and common meates are appointed for the vſe of thys preſent life, but this ſacrament is ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſignify and ſeale vnto vs our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and euerlaſting nouriſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>The tenth ſection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>1.</hi> Wherefore hath the Lorde ordeined &amp; instituted two ſignes in his holy ſupper ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in Baptiſme there is but one only?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To aſſure vs that he doth not feede vs to the halues, but wholly, being not onelye our meate but alſo our drinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>2.</hi> Where is Ieſus Christ nowe according to his humane nature?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In heauen, from whence he ſhall come to iudge the liuing and the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>3.</hi> By what meanes can you then whiche are on the earth receiue him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As I receiue with my hande and my mouth the ſacrament, that is to ſaye, that bread and that wine, for the nouriſhment of thys bodye, euen ſo by the vertue, and power of the holye Ghoſte, I doe inwardly and in my ſoule receiue and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thorowe faythe our Lorde Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:20967:8"/>Chriſt, verye God and verye man, that by him I may liue eternally.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>4.</hi> Doe they which haue no fayth receiue Ieſus Christ in the ſupper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, for Ieſus Chriſte is not receaued but by fayth, yet doe they in deede receiue the ſacrament, but to theyr condemnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>5.</hi> How ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that they make no difference betwene common bread and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wine, and that which is the ſacrament of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of Ieſus Chriſte, whom they reiect and throw from them thorowe theyr vnbeliefe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q <hi>6.</hi> Howe must a man prepare himſelfe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> come worthily to the ſupper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If he haue true repentance of the life y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is paſſed, confeſſing their ſins before God, and amending them towards God and his brethren, ſo much as in him lyeth, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deliberation &amp; purpoſe to be better in time to come, and embracing Ieſus Chriſt by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true fayth in his promiſes and ſacraments for the alone and only ſauior,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. <hi>7.</hi> But hath Ieſus Christe left it vnto our liberty and choyſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether we will go to the ſupper, or not goe to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In forbidding men to reſort thether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, he commandeth all them whiche haue iudgement and diſcretion, to prepare
<pb facs="tcp:20967:8"/>themſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may repaire worthily to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God giue vs all grace to go to it to his honor and glory, and to our ſaluation. So be it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer to be ſayd of children before they ſtudy their leſſon.</head>
               <p>VVherein shall a child addreſſe his vvay, in guiding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe according to thy vvord O Lorde Open our eyes and we shal conſider the merueilous things of thy lavv. Giue vs vnderſtanding, and vve shall keepe thy lavv, yea vve vvil I keepe it vvith our hart.</p>
               <p>O Lord whych art the fountaine of al wiſedom and knowledge, ſeeing it hath pleaſed thee to giue vs the meane to bee taught in our young age, to knowe how to guyde our ſelues holily and honeſtly, in all the reſt of our life hereafter to come, let it pleaſe thee alſo to lighten our vnderſtanding (vvhiche of it ſelfe is blind) that it may comprehend and receiue that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and learning, which ſhall be taught vs, confirme alſo and ſtrengthen our memory to keepe it vvel: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our harts to receiue the ſame vvillingly, &amp; vvith ſuch deſire as is mete, leaſt that thorow our vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, the occaſion that thou doſt offer vnto vs, ſhuld periſh and be loſt. To this end powre vpon vs we pray thee thy holy ſpirit, which is the ſpirite of all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, truth, iudgement, vviſedome and learning, which may make vs able to profit ſo wel that the pains vvhich ſhall be taken in teaching vs be not loſt. And to whatſoeuer ſtudy, that we apply our ſelues, graunt that vve may refer it to the true and right end, vvhich ys to knovv thee, in our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, that vvee may haue ful truſt of our ſaluation and eternall lyfe in thy grace, and may ſerue thee vpryghtlye and purely, accordyng to thy good pleaſure, ſo that al that which we ſhal learn, may be an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to helpe vs therto. And ſeeyng that thou doeſt promyſe to giue wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:20967:9"/>to the little ones, and ſuch as are humble, and on the otherſide to confound the proude in the vanity of their wits and vnderſtandinges: &amp; likewiſe to make thy ſelfe knovvne vnto them that bee of an vpryghte hart, &amp; on the otherſide to make blinde the wicked &amp; vngodly, vve beſech thee to faſhion and ſubdue vs to true humility, that thereby vve may be made apte to learne &amp; obedient alſo, firſt vnto thee, ſecondly vnto our ſuperiors which thou haſt appoynted to gouerne and teach vs. Moreouer vve hartily prayer thee to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and frame our harts, vnfeynedly to ſeeke thee, for ſaking all fleſhly and euil affections, &amp; that we may novv in ſuch ſorte prepare our ſelues, to ſerue thee hereafter in that eſtate &amp; calling, which it ſhal pleaſe thee to ordeine &amp; appoynt for vs, vvhen vve ſhal come to age. Heare vs O father of al mercy, thorovv our Lord Ieſus Chriſte. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALME. 25</bibl>
               <q>The Lord reuealeth his ſecretes, vnto them which feare him, and maketh them to knowe, hys couenaunte.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Hugh Singleton, dwelling in Creede Lane, at the ſigne of the GILDEN TVNN. nere vnto Ludgate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Anno.</hi> 1578.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <p>HS</p>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Hugh Singleton</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20967:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
